Finding Aid for Men's Glee Club (University of Michigan) records 1886-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Men's Glee Club (University of Michigan) Records 1886-2012
University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.
37.1 GB
1 oversize folders
7 oversize volumes
16.5 linear feet
87250 BImu Bimu F19 2
University of Michigan choral group founded in 1859; includes correspondence, administrative records, musical scores, publicity material, photographs, posters and sound recordings in addition to digitized versions of records and born digital audio, video, and still images
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records have been received in periodic accessions since 1960. Included in the collection are records received in Dec. 1985 (donor # 3624 ), and records received from Philip Duey in Dec. 1979 (donor # 6409 ). Additional recordings and material from the 2012 trip to China were received in 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research.
As early as 1846 University of Michigan students met regularly to sing "for pure enjoyment." In 1859 the university formally acknowledged this activity through the establishment of a Glee Club. Michigan's group was the second such college organization formed in the nation.
In its early days the club included from seven to twelve singers who performed college songs, humorous vaudeville numbers and skits. In the 1870s the larger group began to divide into smaller performing units, trios and quartets, which allowed for greater individual recognition. In the 1880s the club began to tour and in 1884 the organization made its first excursion outside of the state. Because of the demands of touring the size of the club was expanded, first to sixteen members, four men per part, and by the turn of the century to around fifty members.
After World War I the club experienced difficult times. A lack of sound musical programs led to declining audiences, and in 1920 a disastrous West Coast tour lost so much money that the club was unable to tour for five years. In 1921, as part of an effort to revive itself, the club became part of the Michigan Union. In 1922 the name "Men's Glee Club" was formally adopted and the club experimented with new music. An all classical format was first adopted, and when this proved unsuccessful it was changed to the balanced program of classical, humorous and college songs still used today. The club also began to formally participate in the annual Michigan Union Operas, an all male comedy review.
All of these changes led to a revival in the club's fortunes. Touring was resumed, which eventually caused the club to withdraw from the Union Operas, because the two groups' separate touring schedules made it impossible for members to participate in both. In 1943 the club formally ended its affiliation with the Union and resumed its prior status, as an independent student organization.
After World War II the club evolved new traditions and expanded its touring activity. In 1952 the club began the Fall custom of singing with the Glee Club of a school that had played the University of Michigan that day in a football game. In 1955 the popular double quartet, the Friars, was first organized. 1955 also marked the club's first European tour, which was followed by international tours in 1959, 1963, 1967, 1971, 1978, 1989, and 1992. The tours of 1959 and 1963 were highlighted by victories at the International Musical Eisteddfod in Llangollen, Wales. 2012 saw the club embark on a successful tour of the People's Republic of China.
When the club was first organized, and for many years thereafter, musical directorship was entrusted to a club member. In the 1870s and 1880s, however, the club began to experiment with hiring a professional director, usually a music teacher from the Ann Arbor area. In 1894 the club returned to appointing one of their own members as director, but the idea of hiring a professional remained and in 1908 the club resumed the practice of hiring a director.
Professional Director's of the Men's Glee Club
1885-1889 Ross G. Cole
1890-1892 Albert A. Stanley
1892-1893 Silas R. Mills
1908-1911 Earle Killeen
1911-1914 William A. Howland
1914-1919 Theodore Harrison
1919-1920 Russell Carter
1920-1922 Frank L. Thomas
1922-1924 George O. Bowen
1924-1930 Theodore Harrison
1930-1931 Arthur Hackett
1931-1947 David E. Mattern
1947-1955 Philip A. Duey
1955-1956 Walter S. Collins (acting)
1956-1969 Philip A. Duey
1969-1975 Willis C. Patterson
1975-1981 Leonard Johnson
1981-1987 Patrick Gardner
1987-1988 Bradley Bloom
1988-2002 Jerry Blackstone
2002-2005 Stephen Lusmann
2005-2011 Paul Rardin
2012- Eugene Rogers
The records of the Men's Glee Club date from 1886 to 2012 and were received in several major accessions. The first accession, covering 1886-1985 and 1991, includes four linear feet of manuscript, printed, and photographic material as well as posters, scrapbooks, and sound recordings in a variety of formats. The first accession has been divided into five series: Chronological File, Philip A. Duey Material, Photographs, Sound Recordings, Scrapbooks, and Archived Website.
The 1995 accession of the records of the Men's Glee Club were comprised of two linear feet of correspondence, photographs, and topical files ranging from 1919 to 1994. Items of particular interest include a folder of historical writings, which provides anecdotes, reflections, and facts about the club prepared for an exhibit on club history. The Press Releases folder is also of note, as it reflects information given out by the club to newspapers and other media of the towns they visited. Both of these folders are found in the Topical series. The records of this accession are divided into 3 series: Correspondence, Topical, and Visual Materials.
The 2010 accession to the University of Michigan Men's Glee Club records is organized into one series. The Sound Recordings series, 1952-1987, (10 linear feet) is comprised of University of Michigan Men's Glee Club concert recordings, including its annual fall and spring concert series. Many of the boxes of tape reel also include a concert program and concert set list.
The 2012 accession consisted entirely of digital materials (scanned images, audio files, video files, and still images) that added content to the Chronological Files series and established a China Concert Tour series.
Subjects:
Friars (Musical group); Michigan Union Opera.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Choral singing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material
Duey, Philip A., d. 1982.; Friars (Musical group); Mandolin Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Contributors:
Duey, Philip A., d. 1982.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- Chronological File
  (BHL deposit ID: 87250_0002)
  The Chronological File represents the basic records of the collection. Arranged by academic year, it consists primarily of printed concert programs, newspaper clippings and other publicity material, occasional financial records (generally summary statements of club finances for an academic year), details regarding tours (particularly the annual spring tour), and minutes. Many posters were included in the Chronological File. Unfolded posters have been housed separately in an oversized folder. This series contains four individual documents of particular note. A fifteen page club history written by John Payne is found in 1958-1959. Narrative logs of the club's international trips in 1955, 1959 and 1967 were maintained and are filed in the appropriate years. Chronological File materials from 1886-1969 have been scanned and these digital versions may be found in the Bentley Library's digital repository.
  The 2012 additions to the Chronological Files series include digitized images of content in the first two boxes of the series, spanning the years 1886-1969. Glee Club members scanned this content as part of an organizational project in 2011. Digital versions of Laudes, the official newsletter of the Men's Glee Club, were also part of the addition. These newsletters were published biannually and span the years 2000-2011 (with the Fall 2009 issue missing from the accession). Both the original and digital copies have been retained.[BHL deposit ID: 87250_0002]
  - 1886-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1911/121-1941/42, 28 folders (Box 1)
  - 1944/45-1956/957, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - 1957/58-1968/69, 21 folders (Box 2)
  - 1969/70-1984/85, 17 folders (Box 3)
  - Undated
    - General (Box 3)
    - Songs (Box 3)
    - Plays, Skits and Stories (Box 3)
    - Programs (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Other Publicity (Box 3)
  - "Laudes" (official newsletter) 2000-2011
- Philip A. Duey
  The Philip A. Duey Material consists of only two folders, one detailing the radio career of the Club's one time director before he came to Ann Arbor and the other containing miscellaneous personal material. A few newspaper clippings about Duey before he came to the University of Michigan are found in the appropriate chronological folder, particularly 1946-1947.
  - Radio Career (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Photographs and Posters (see also boxes 5, 6 and 8)
  The Photographs (some oversize) consist primarily of group pictures, tour pictures, photos of the Novelaires and the Friars, Philip Duey photographs, and a few Union Opera pictures. A few photographs are also located in the Chronological File.
  - Group Photos
    - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - With Pat Boone and Dinah Shore (Box 3)
    - Novelaires and Friars (Box 3)
    - Rehearsals (Box 3)
  - Individuals
    - General (Box 3)
    - Philip A. Duey (Box 3)
  - Tours
    - General (Box 3)
    - 1896, 1959, 1963, 1971 (negatives only), 1978 (8 envelopes) (Box 3)
- Sound Recordings
  Sound Recordings include tape recordings made in 1952 and 1967 of club songs, a long playing record album of the 1959 club centennial spring concert, and a 1991 compact disc comprised of concert recordings.
  - 1953, 3 reels tape recordings, 7" 15 ips (Box 4)
  - 1959, 33-1/3 long play disc of Centennial Concert (Box 4)
  - 1967, 4 reels tape recordings, 7" 7.5 ips (Box 4)
  - "Michigan Songs" circa 1978, 1 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - 1988-89 (live recordings), 1 compact disc (Box 4)
- Photographs and Posters
  - Photos (Box 5)
  - Photos (Box 6)
    (continued)
- Correspondence
  Arranged chronologically by season, the Correspondence series mostly reflects the negotiations the club's business manager conducted to secure appearances for the club. The bulk of the letters come from the early 1920s, with two additional folders from the late 1930s. The "1923 West Coast Trip" folder gives the most accurate representation of the often arduous process taken to secure dates and venues for tours. Of note is a letter of thanks from President Gerald R. Ford
  - 1919-1920 (Box 7)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 7)
  - 1923 (West Coast Trip) (Box 7)
  - 1923-1924 (Box 7)
  - 1937-1938 (Box 7)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Gerald R. Ford 1975 (Box 7)
- Topical
  The Topical file deals largely with items documenting the tours upon which the Men's Glee Club frequently embarked. The performance contracts, though not complete, provide a useful and extensive overview of the types of places, venues, and dates the club played and the terms and conditions they demanded. The "Constitution and By-Laws" folder gives an overview of Glee Club policies and administrative operations. The folders in the "Tours" subseries are comprised of materials the club put together in preparation for travel and include itineraries and guides to their destinations.
  - Account Book 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Account Book 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - City and County of Denver Proclamation 2010 (Box 7)
  - Constitution and By-laws (Box 7)
  - Contracts
    - 1922-1926 (Box 7)
    - 1947-1954 (Box 7)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 7)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 7)
    - 1962-1977 (Box 7)
    - 1987-1993 (Box 7)
  - Count Basie Concert 1957 (Box 7)
  - Historical Writings (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7)
  - Novelaires 1950 (Box 7)
  - Press Releases (Box 7)
  - Tours
    - China 2012 (Box 7)
    - Eastern and Central Europe 1992 (Box 7)
    - Llangollen International Musical Eisteddfod undated (Box 7)
    - Midwest 1994 (Box 7)
    - Orient 1989 (Box 7)
    - Schedules 1948-1959 (Box 7)
    - Schedules 1985-1993 (Box 7)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series gives a view of club activities from several different eras. "Group Portraits" show the Glee Club posing for photos and contains photos of the club singing or performing other activities. The "Publicity Shots" provide an interesting window to the era when the Glee Club participated in the all-male Michigan Union Operas. The record group also holds an extensive number of color snapshots with negatives of the club's 1987 tour. An oversized folder of publicity posters forms another section of visual materials. Two photo albums and a film of the club's 1964 appearance on the Perry Como television show round out the series.
  - Photographs
    - Conductors (Box 8)
    - Friars (Box 8)
    - Group Portraits, Dated (Box 8)
    - Group Portraits, Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Groups, Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Individuals (Box 8)
    - Officers (Box 8)
    - Performance 1986 (Box 8)
    - Publicity Shots (Box 8)
    - Reunion (Box 8)
    - Soloists (Box 8)
    - Tour 1936 (Upper Peninsula) (Box 8)
    - Tour 1987, 9 envelopes (Box 8)
    - Tour 1989 (China) (Box 8)
  - Photo Albums
    - European Tour 1985 (Box 8)
    - East Coast Tour 1988 (Box 8)
  - Film (16mm)
    - Appearance on the Perry Como Show 1964 (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks (BImu/F19)
  The Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically and primarily contain newspaper clippings and programs.
  - 1923 [1] (Box 8)
  - 1938 [2] (Box 8)
  - 1955 European Tour [Special Location: B283/3] (Box 8)
  - 1960-1961 [3] (Box 8)
  - 1964 [4] (Box 8)
  - 1966-1967 World Tour [5] (Box 8)
  - 1967-1968 [6] (Box 8)
- Sound Recordings 1952-1987
  The Sound Recordings series, 1952-1987, (10 linear feet) is comprised of University of Michigan Men's Glee Club concert recordings, including its annual fall and spring concert series. Many of the boxes of tape reel also include a concert program and concert set list.
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club May 10, 1952, 3 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, May 25; 1952, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Philip A. Duey," 25 July 1952, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Cornell University Glee Club, 7 November 1952, 3 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, May16 1953, 2 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Ohio State University Glee Club Joint Concert November 21, 1953, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club May 20, 1955, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & University of Illinois Varsity Glee Club Joint Concert November 10, 1956, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Miscellaneous College Songs," June 14, 1957, 1 reels (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 99th Annual Spring Concert May 10, 1958, 5 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "The Pat Boone Show," May 15,1958, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Michigan Songs," July 16, 1958, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Concert Songs," July 16, 1958, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Indiana University Singing Hoosiers Combined Concert November 15, 1958, 2 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 101st Annual Spring Concert May 14, 1960, 2 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & University of Illinois Glee Club Combined Concert, November 5 1960, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 102nd Annual Spring Concert May 13, 1961, 2 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Duke University Glee Club Combined Concert November 4, 1961, 2 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "On Tour," December 26, 1961, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "On Tour," December 28, 1961, 1 reels (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 103rd Annual Spring Concert May 12, 1962, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Pressing Master June 20, 1962, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, University Choir, and University of Michigan All-State Choir October 21, 1962, 1 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & University of Wisconsin Glee Club Combine Concert November 3, 1962, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club May 18, 1963, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 105th Annual Spring Concert April 18, 1964, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Spring Concert Pressing Master June 19, 1964, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Chor der Singeleiter Lübeck," 25 October 1964, 1 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & University of Illinois Glee Club Combine Concert November 7, 1964, 2 reels (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 106th Annual Spring Concert March 27, 1965, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Kwansei Gakuin Glee Club October 6, 1965, 1 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & New York University Glee Club Combined Concert October 30, 1965, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 107th Annual Spring Concert April 2, 1966, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Pressing Master June 21, 1966, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 3rd Annual Bandorama October 14, 1966, 1 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Northwestern University Glee Club Joint Concert November 12, 1966, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Michigan Songs," March 9, 1967, 1 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 108th Annual Spring Concert, April 11, 967, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 108th Annual Spring Concert Pressing Master, 11 June 1967, 2 reels (Box 12)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Ohio State University Glee Club Join Concert November 4, 1967, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Studio Showcase January 10, 1968, 1 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 109th Annual Spring Concert March 23, 1968, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 109th Annual Spring Concert Pressing Master March 23, 1968, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & University of Illinois Varsity Glee Club Join Concert November 9, 1968, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "White Tie and Tails," March 29 1969, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Pressing Master Side 1 June 22, 1969, 1 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Pressing Master Side 2 June 22, 1969, 1 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Ohio State University Men's Glee Club Joint Concert November 22, 1969, 2 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 1970, 1 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Michigan Songs," January 7, 1970, 1 reels (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 1971, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club March 20, 1971, 2 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Luxembourg and Wales July 1971, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club November 6, 1971, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club March 24, 1972, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club March 25, 1972, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Seattle, Washington May 1973, 3 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Morehouse College Fall Concert November 9, 1973, 2 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 114th Annual Spring Concert, 30 March 1974, 3 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club& Ohio State University 115th Fall Concert, 16 November 1974, 3 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Christmas 1974, 1 reels (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 115th Annual Spring Concert April 12, 1975, 3 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 115th Fall Concert November 22, 1975, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 116th Annual Spring Concert April 10, 1976, 3 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 117th Fall Concert November 13, 1976, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Songs of Michigan" Pressing Master 1977, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 117th Annual Spring Concert April 2, 1977, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 118th Fall Concert and Arbors, 19 November 1977, 3 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 118th Annual Spring Concert March 18, 1978, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Vienna I & II 1978, 2 reels (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club St. Blasius 1978, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 119th Fall Concert & Purdue University Men's Glee Club November 18, 1978, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 120th Annual Spring Concert April 7, 1979, 1 reels (Box 16)
  - The Friars "Quadraphenomena" Pressing Master, 20, 27, 29 June 1979, 1 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 120th Fall Concert & Wayne State University Men's Glee Club November 17, 1979, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, University of Michigan Symphony Orchestra, & University of Michigan Chamber Orchestra April 13, 1980, 1 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 120th Annual Spring Concert April 19, 1980, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - The Friar's Silver Anniversary November 15, 1980, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Songs of Michigan," May 14, 1981, 1 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 122nd Fall Concert & Ohio State University Men's Glee Club November 21, 1981, 3 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 123rd Fall Concert Dedicated to Phillip Duey November 13, 1982, 2 reels (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & The California State University, Hayward, Spring 1983, 2 reels (Box 17)
  - 27th Best Concert Ever The Friars and The Grunyons March 25, 1983, 4 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 123rd Annual Spring Concert April 16, 1983, 2 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 124th Annual Spring Concert April 7, 1984, 1 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 125th Anniversary Pressing Master June 25, 1894, July 2, 1984, 1 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 125th Fall Concert and Reunion Concert November 10, 1984, 4 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 125th Annual Spring Concert April 13, 1985, 2 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Christmas Master Ta[e, October 14,1985, 1 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 126th Fall Concert with the University of Illinois November 23, 1985, 3 reels (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 126th Spring Concert, April 12 1986, 2 reels (Box 18)